The hotel is built on a mangrove island, which is very different from a solid land island.
The terrain here is acidic, salty, and unstable, making work difficult.
When we arrived, many areas were still flooded, especially during the rainy season.
In the first phase of construction, all the land was redistributed to raise the ground level and prevent future flooding.
This land was also used to elevate the pathways and create various secret gardens.
To stabilize the land, a large amount of gravel and sand was needed.
From there, the access points were defined and the areas intended for gardens were marked.
With the goal of gaining more land, we decided to create a natural lake,
digging up to 2.5 meters deep with a team of 20 people and two extraction pumps running all day.
Since the amount of land was still insufficient, I proposed creating a river that could become a new attraction in the future.
Everything must be brought from the main island and transported by boat.
Everything is unloaded by hand because we cannot use machinery.
We also faced the presence of chytras, which we fought with a special treatment exclusive to Nayara.
Once the land was stabilized, we began testing with plants.
Many species didn't adapt, but after research, we developed a suitable list.
Having mastered this phase, I implemented a propagation system using mother plants.
Today, 75% of the plants come from our own nursery.
Vision. To be the most exclusive and sustainable luxury destination in the Caribbean.
Recognized worldwide for our ability to create exceptional experiences that connect our guests with nature in a unique and surprising way.
We see ourselves as a benchmark in luxury hospitality, where every detail is designed to surprise, inspire, and exceed our visitors' expectations,
while maintaining a constant commitment to environmental preservation and innovation in every aspect of our service.
Mission. To create a unique and unforgettable experience that harmoniously combines luxury, nature, and culture, offering our guests a dream escape.
We commit to providing exceptional service, focusing on sustainability and respect for the environment,
so that every visitor lives an extraordinary experience, surrounded by natural beauty and a welcoming atmosphere,
where the island's magic and Balinese style blend to awaken the senses and the imagination.
Hello, I'm Scott Dinsmore, General Manager of Nayara Bocas del Toro. Welcome.
Hello, I'm Jorge Méndez, Operations Manager at Nayara Bocas del Toro. Welcome.
Hello, my name is Yorin Batista, I'm the restaurant supervisor at Nayara Bocas del Toro. Welcome.
Hello, my name is Liz, welcome to Nayara. I'm part of the team responsible for logistics and reservations.
We're happy to have you as part of this big family. Welcome.
Hello, my name is Tanisha Howell, and I'm the Guest Experience Manager. Welcome to Nayara Bocas del Toro. We're very happy to have you on this team.
Hello, welcome to Nayara Bocas del Toro. My name is David Jiménez; I'm part of the management team. I'm also on the construction team as Project Manager. Welcome to the family.
Hello, good morning. Welcome to the Nayara Hotel group. I'm Cédric, the hotel's landscape architect and responsible for maintaining all garden areas. Welcome.
Hello, my name is Felipe Caballero. I'm the Maintenance Manager at Nayara Hotel. Welcome to the team.
Hello, how are you? My name is Charney Francois. I'm the Human Resources Manager. We are very happy to have you join our family. Welcome.
Hello, my name is Leonel Gude. I'm in charge of the captains. Welcome to Nayara.
Hello, my name is Ori El Burado. I'm the CEO of Nayara Bocas. Welcome to the team. Welcome to our big family.
Hello, how are you? My name is Raúl Gustavos. I'm the Head of Housekeeping and oversee rooms, common area cleaning, and laundry. We're very happy to have you in this Nayara Bocas del Toro family.
Hello, my name is Nancy. I'm the Financial Director here at Nayara. I was fortunate to join this adventure even before the hotel opened. So, I've seen how the project has evolved from the beginning.
If you're looking for a united, dynamic, and passionate team, come join us. We still have many wonderful things to achieve.
The organizational culture at our resort focuses on a passion for delivering unforgettable experiences with an emphasis on authentic hospitality and respect for nature.
We foster a work environment where every team member is an ambassador of exceptional service, acting with courtesy, kindness, and a deep sense of responsibility towards our guests and the environment.
We believe teamwork, creativity, and commitment to excellence are essential to creating an environment that inspires both our employees and our visitors.
Collaboration with the local community and respect for indigenous cultures are fundamental pillars in our organizational philosophy and are reinforced as institutional values here.
Exceptional hospitality: every guest is treated as a special member, providing warm, personalized, and attentive service that exceeds their expectations.
Sustainability: committed to environmental preservation, we adopt eco-friendly practices that protect our natural resources and minimize the impact of our operations on the island.
Innovation: we constantly seek new ways to surprise and delight our guests, implementing creative solutions that enhance every experience.
Authenticity: we promote a genuine connection with nature and culture, providing experiences that reflect the island's essence and Balinese heritage.
Respect and responsibility: we encourage a respectful relationship with both our environment and the local community, focusing on sustainable development and the well-being of future generations.
LHW, The Leading Hotels of the World
Being part of LHW is more than a distinction; it's a validation of quality and authenticity.
LHW stands for The Leading Hotels of the World, an exclusive network of independent luxury hotels around the world, founded in 1928.
This association brings together unique properties distinguished by their level of service, history, design, and authenticity.
Joining LHW requires undergoing a rigorous process that includes a formal application, standards review, and a confidential audit evaluating more than 800 criteria.
Only those who reach the highest level of hospitality, originality, and excellence gain access to this network.
For Nayara, this affiliation is an opportunity to grow, share, and compete with the world's best without losing its identity.
Now, let's continue with Green Globe.
Green Globe is an international organization dedicated to sustainability certification in the tourism and hospitality industry.
Its main goal is to promote responsible practices toward the environment, society, and the economy,
helping businesses in the sector operate more sustainably.
What does Green Globe handle?
Certifying the sustainability of hotels, resorts, convention centers, travel agencies, tourist attractions, and destinations.
Auditing environmental, social, and economic practices to ensure companies meet certain international sustainability criteria.
Providing continuous improvement tools such as performance reports and recommendations to reduce environmental impact and improve sustainable management.
What requirements must a company meet to join Green Globe?
To obtain Green Globe certification, a company must meet more than 50% of the 44 basic criteria grouped into four main areas.
Environmental sustainability.
This refers to efficient use of energy and water, waste management and recycling, protection of biodiversity and local ecosystems, and reduction of carbon emissions.
Sustainable management.
This involves sustainability policies integrated into business strategy, staff training on environmental and social issues, evaluation and control of operational impact.
Social responsibility.
Respect for local culture and community.
Inclusion of the community in decision-making and business benefits.
Fair and safe working conditions.
Cultural and economic aspects.
Promotion of local culture and heritage.
Support for local products and suppliers.
Economic transparency.
The certification process starts with membership in Green Globe.
An initial assessment.
Audit by an independent verifier.
Certification is granted.
Valid for one year and renewable.
Continuous improvements and regular audits.